Um my name is Benjamin Crockett and I'm
delighted to be here with my good friend
uh Father Kenny Yang.
>> Hi Ben.
>> As as we you know as as we as we look at
the the emerging technology that is that
is changing you know the way we think
about work and education at the same
time. Um I think the Catholic vision of
education is something different than
maybe the secular model.
>> Yeah. So if we go back to the very
founding of universities right
university of Bolognia right 1088 or
Oxford Paris Salamanca right the first
universities
Catholic church had a lot to do with the
founding of universities and
universities were before cathedral
schools right so what were the idea of
university back then well it's what we
often call today liberal arts right So
they're teaching the trivium,
quadrivium, right? Some grammar, logic,
rhetoric, and then the sciences, right?
You have mathematics, music, arithmetic,
and then astronomy, right? So there's a
trivium, quadrivium. These are sciences
that will make you free. Hence the name
liberal arts, right? So arts, sciences
that free a human person to what? To do
the good. Freedom is not autonomy,
right?
freedom is the freedom the ability to do
the good I I I want to do right that's
the idea of freedom now if we fast
forward to the 20th century as you said
nowadays people go to college without
thinking right and then okay I just want
to get a paper right then that piece of
paper that certifies that I've done this
and then I want to get a job make money
etc so the idea of education is has been
shifted towards oh this is learning
something pract practical to do, right?
It's like learning a trade, right? So,
it's no longer
offering this freedom, right? At least
in the idea of of those studying, right?
How can we learn from let's say
trinitarian theology so we can focus our
education in in in its original sense.
So, you know, one of the greatest
contributions of St. Thomas Aquinus was
defining divine person as subsisting
relation right so what distinguishes the
father from the son and the spirit right
they're all they're god and they create
uh together right so what distinguishes
a person from the other two and the
father is paternity right he's father he
begat the son right and the son is
distinguished by this relation of
affiliation towards the father and the
father and the son together spirate
right breathe the holy spirit so it's
the relation that distinguishes the
divine persons and we learn that in
education relation relationships
occupy central central place as well
right [clears throat] I had a professor
back in pmplona he taught me moral
theology um Jose Maria Parado
he he's a doctor as well. So he studied
medicine before becoming a priest and
theologian.
I remember one thing he told us about
his studies in medicine. Right nowadays
he said you you have great books of
medicine. You have books that connect
you to the internet where you can find a
three-dimensional you know illustration
of heart right so you have everything
you want to study by yourself
to self teach yourself right medicine
and presupposing that the students who
who do study medicine are the greatest
students right the brightest there and
what reasons do they have to come to
class and listen to this doctor or
professor talking about something they
could learn elsewhere. So a classium
part has to be somehow novel, engaging,
adding something otherwise they would
study better elsewhere. I mean these are
not lazy or slow students right they
could do better elsewhere. So I think
education here like teaching at the
university level is also offering
something they can't get elsewhere. And
what is it right? I've been thinking a
lot about this. What is it that I as an
educator as a teacher lecturer can offer
that they couldn't obtain elsewhere?
It's not the information. It's not the
data. I think AI can give you better.
I don't know if it's better, but give
you data at at least the internet has a
lot of information. But I can offer this
human relationship that's not present
on the internet.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and that wisdom of
accompanyment like I think that that
like that possibility to make lifelong
friendships like I think about um about
my experience at the university um I
studied at University of California
Berkeley for my undergrad and I would
say that while the classes were
excellent and the professors were
wonderful the most transformative
aspects of my education were outside of
class. It was those relationships, it
was those first experiences with with
people and and and situations. It was um
it was traversing that that life
experience of you know from 18 to 22
there's a lot of growth that happens.
You figure out kind of who you are and I
feel like as much as I I I applaud
online universities and and you know
ways for people to work uh and to study
from home and to continue to be lifelong
learners. I think that's something
beautiful about about this moment in
time that people can go back to class. I
think that you miss a big part of the
university experience if you don't make
a relationship with your with your
professors, with your mentors, with your
tutors. Um, and I and I'm and I am
worried about that because I I think
also that that that aspect of isolating
yourself at home and just, you know,
let's say getting the the raw analytics
or the raw data. Um, like I see that
also with people wanting to do remote
working. While that's really comfortable
and wonderful for a lot of things, I I
do think that that shared experience is
part of what it means to be human. And I
and I am worried about that. And I and I
think that that kind of spirals into all
the other issues, you know, we we look
at when when you mention, you know,
attention deficit. um the ability to
really work in a quiet space like in a
library and read a book for a period of
time and really like highlight and read
that like I feel like communication and
relationships are things that that the
current younger generations are going to
be struggling with are things that
they're going to really have to be
working on.
>> Oh yeah, even movies. I mean people have
difficulties watching movies nowadays
because you know
>> I used to be so excited to go to the
movies. I was like yes a three-hour
movie fantastic. Don't we prefer like
short form contents and everything
because you know you have to maintain
your attention for 2 hours 3 hours for
movie
>> and like like a big screen like a big
screen like movie theater like that's
absolute focus whereas now like oh I'll
have a small you know home home cinema
but I'll also have my cell phone and
I'll also have maybe something my
computer out like there'll be three
screens going out and people I mean I I
love that selectivity of being able to
choose what you want but at the same
time there has to be a moment where
there's an absolute like there there's
an you know like like you go to mass
it's like okay it's phone turned off I'm
absolely absolutely focused uh
classroom. I'm absolutely focused on the
professor, cinema, theater, whatever.
Like I'm I'm focused on the art form. Um
do you um father what do you where do
you think because I I feel this is
another thing I I I heard as I was
preparing for this interview. Um there
were a lot of teachers and I think this
is probably more in like primary school
and and in secondary school education
where the teachers also feel that
because um the formation that happened
that typically used to happen in the
household um is not happening as much as
it used to as as families you know
fracture as as kind of the the kids
coming from broken households. It's much
more common. Um they they say that
they're the teachers are having are
finding themselves having to do a lot of
other things outside of just you know
teaching mathematics or or history class
and and that of course then spirals into
you know the the the issues surrounding
cell phones, smartphones, all that stuff
that kind of contribute to more pressure
and anxiety on children, isolation
because what used to be a day at the
park is now a day at home by yourself as
we're all zooming in together doing you
know. Um do you do you do you find that
also at the graduate level and at the at
the university level that that students
are having by and large a more difficult
time just focusing on the material?
>> Yes, I think so. Right. You're right
because family is supposed to be the
first school, right? The first place
where you're you get educated. You you
guys should be explaining how we live,
right? Yeah.
>> And then there there are so many people
who don't obtain this first primary
education in in the family as you said,
right? [clears throat] And yeah, I was
going to jump into what you said earlier
as well that when we were in the period
of COVID, right? We we got really
excited about this all this online
thing, right? Oh, we can actually attend
our classes online, right? We can have
this online session, webinars and
everything. Now, at least me personally,
I I really I don't despise online
meetings, right? I don't despise online
encounters, but I long for in-person
events, right? I think experience like,
you know, co I don't want to say it's
good, but it teaches us a lot of things.
It it shows manifests what we really
value as human persons. Oh, we value
this in-person encounters, right?
And this is very important in theology,
right? There's an expression actually in
Italian that's very descriptive of this
is this is not good. Okay? is theologia
fatavolino
is probably can be translated into
English as office theology right like a
theology done at an office right sitting
probably you you might look really
hardworking right you're thinking about
one thing but you're isolated so you
don't really value what's important you
don't have the scope and perview context
right dialogue
>> it's more theory than than anything
actually real
>> exactly it's theory right it's theory
But theology has always been done in the
church, meaning in in the community of
Christians, right? It's done by talking
to others, is done by responding to
other people's objections. It's done by,
you know, a public disputes in in the
medieval times. That's what theology is.
You are in dialogue. You're in touch
with people who are doing the same thing
as well, right? So, we're always doing
it as a community, never as an
individual. That that is interesting
that that um you're saying as a
community rather than an individual. I
feel that one of the one of the problems
that I I think of when I was going
through my educational park course um
was that it was very much an individual
pursuit. Okay. I was I was under
pressure to get good grades. I was under
pressure to do extracurriculars. I was
under pressure and it wasn't me versus
my other classmates necessarily, but
there was I mean and I think healthy
competition is wonderful, but it was not
at all me as a member of the community.
I mean, it was very much I need to go to
a good school and I need to do whatever
I can to get to a good school. And I
know in my in my class like there was an
enormous amount of students who had
that, but it was it was very much
individually motivated. And I and and
once again like I I think competition,
healthy competition is great because it
can make you strive to be your best. But
I I look at that and there's two things
I would say about that. I wonder how we
can get back to a communal aspect and
and I think maybe one of the things that
hurts that is that at least in the US
which I think is a good thing but that
people go far away to the colleges like
I mean there are people who go to the
state school just next door but a lot of
people have ambitions to go to the best
schools and they're often times you know
they're far away but uh but another
aspect that I'm that I'd be curious
father to hear from you is is so what
would that what would a communal
educational format look like where
everyone is genuinely rooting for
everyone um rather and then okay what
can I get you know what can I how can I
get ahead and also um when I was going
to school even though there was a lot of
pressure there was a level of optimism
of okay cool well I get to good college
and then I'll get a good job and and you
know the the world is mine in a sense
and I feel now when I talk to some
members of my family and some friends
who have have kids who are you know in
that high school age there isn't that
same optimism it's more it feels more
like a survival educational format like
gosh I just I need to get a a postoc so
that maybe hopefully I can get a
teaching position maybe if I'm lucky or
I need to do this thing so I can just
barely sneak by. You know, I feel like
there's a feeling and I don't know,
father, if you feel the same thing, but
there isn't that same optimism as there
was maybe 10 years ago. And I wonder if
this the the kind of the technological
vision of well AI is just going to take
all the jobs or you know some some
version of that if if that if you feel
that as well or if you see that as well.
>> Yeah, I think so in a sense. [snorts]
Yeah, we forget sometimes that we
we study to know the truth, right? To
it's some truth is something to be
pursued for for its own sake, right? And
and I think we are acquiring
unconsciously this utilitarian
vision [clears throat] of education,
right? Oh, I I I I got to do this
because I and when this education does
not guarantee me getting that, you know,
objective, then I I lose passion. I lose
interest in education in itself, right?
So, I think of course we got to be very
practical. We got to survive in the
world, get a job and everything, right?
So I think it's a good balance that we
have to try to seek between you know
okay I know that I learned because as a
human person I was created by God to
know the truth right that's one of the
basic human instincts Thomas Aquinus
says it and then we want to know the
truth nobody likes being lied to right
and that's a basic human instinct like
looking for food right personal survival
survival of the species etc so we want
know the truth and that's why I learn
now our grading system sometimes is not
very helpful is it so there's a lot to
say about this right I I read an article
not not a very long time ago about
ungrading so
an author in I think in the states if
I'm not mistaken is proposing ungrading
right not grading your students instead
we can let them decide the grade they
want at the beginning of the course and
then the task of the teacher is to help
that student achieve that grade. So I I
want to get a B, right? Oh, I want to
get an A. Then okay, let me help you. So
if that student you the teacher says
that, oh, you you get a B. You wanted an
A, but you get a B. It's not like I'm
punishing you, but you could have done a
little bit more to achieve your goal,
right? You wanted an A, right? So it's
like helping the students is is a great
idea, I think, in in in an ideal world,
right? [laughter] in in our current
world well uh at least we have systems
in place etc. But I think uh all
teachers, every teacher can at least do
something in order to uh focus the
grading not on the result but on the
process right so
education or learning a course right a c
a university course for example is
getting from point A to point B right
okay okay what's the objective here okay
I want to help my students know the
trinity better Right? That that's that's
the goal, right? Know the trinity better
and then not only know it conceptually,
academically if you want, but also know
how knowing the trinity better can
change your life, change your prayer
life, change your social life as well.
So that's the goal. And then getting
from point A to point B is where I want
to grade, right? Okay. How are you
progressing in this? Now this is very
abstract and you know is every person is
different. So I think dedicating time to
every student is also important right
and and this is where at least I try to
shift my methodology um to this
direction. And father, do you think as
um you know I mean hopefully uh with you
know with AI um teachers will be able to
dedicate more time to their students
with you know busy work um admin admin
stuff um streamlining some of those
tasks with AI. I I we hope at least that
that AI is going to permit them so that
the teachers can can shine a light more
on on the on the students needs. Do you
on the practical level today do you how
are you using AI? Are you finding it
being a useful tool um to streamline
those tasks so that you can dedicate
more time to the the students?
>> Of course. Of course. Yeah. I guess I
use AI every day for different things
for Yeah. translating something, for
example. That's a task I use AI for,
right? Because it does quite a good job
uh in translating text, right? Or
writing emails to to students or
[clears throat] to colleagues and
everything. you know, drafting a good a
good email is just as important as
having an important message, right?
Because when an email is ambiguous, it's
not clear and people will be um asking
you again and it's a lot of back and
forth that really consumes your time.
So, I use AF for that as well for a lot
of just administrative task, right? Um
dividing my students into groups, right?
Or and then for proof reading as well.
AI is I find it useful for proof reading
text before you might pay somebody to do
it for you, right? Or and but now you
have AI to help you with it. Uh it's
it's very helpful in this direction I
think. And then as you said, it helps me
dedicate time for students in ways I I I
did less before. Mhm.
>> And then, father, there's the kind of
the the the stresses that I I I've read
and I've spoken a few to a few teachers
around AI of um of the authenticity of
of the work. So, you know, people
wondering, okay, well, the the college
essay was a standard, you know,
assignment that would be assigned to
almost every student regardless of of
the classes they're taking. They're
going to be doing several um you know,
college essays per term. Uh history,
English, you know, ethics, you know,
theology. Um, of course with um, you
know, with chat GBT for example, uh,
professors have talked about, okay,
well, how do we how do we catch for
plagiarism? How do we, you know, help
students really do that hard work of of
doing the research for the for the
paper, learning sentence structures,
really making a good argument? How how
are you and your your colleagues um,
handling essay formats like um, in this
age of AI,
>> right?
Yeah, we had a discussion about this not
not a very long time ago. Me and my
colleagues, the faculty, right? This is
very pressing problem. I think on the
one hand, we are convinced that we are
not teaching our students to do what AI
can do better, right? That's important
to say, right? Because okay, I don't
want to teach my students to do better
what should do what AI could do better.
So for at least this is what I do,
right? uh um there are different
approaches and I might be wrong as well.
I might change this next year, right?
But at least this year I do not assign
papers because as you said we can
generate papers using artificial
intelligence. Instead I focus more on
oral exams right on tutorial groups
where students will get together with
myself as well and then I will
try to stimulate debates discussions and
hopefully this tutorial groups will also
be there are study groups maybe right if
they they find themselves at ease. So
it's it's shifting the focus to what's
more in person more direct right
immediate so to non-mediated formats of
exams at the same time though so uh
we cannot ditch writing as if it's not
important right so okay I don't assign
papers but I'm not saying that okay
forget about writing no because for me
myself at least writing is thinking
right for me too
>> yeah right so when I All right. I think
>> Yeah.
>> And to think I need to write.
>> Yeah. I need I need to talk out loud. I
need to think. I need to write. It's
it's a whole it's a circle. And then the
the thought becomes better as you write
it down because then it becomes real and
you're like, "Oh, that's not exactly
what I meant. How do you change it?"
It's
>> exactly.
>> I think it's a very important part of
the the process. And then father um just
to to jump on that um and this might be
you know almost an impossible question
in the sense that I I' I've been
thinking about it a lot is what what is
the difference? So I mean I I agree that
you're teaching students to do something
different than an artificial
intelligence can just replicate or give
the the simulation of of intelligence.
But what in your mind what is what is
the difference between human knowledge
which of course is earned and worked for
and and that whole process versus
something that seems like a simulation
of it like a you know an artificial you
know intelligence in that sense like
what what is the difference because I
think that that's where the the fault
line of course is where what you are
doing is very different than what can be
simply reproduced. Well, there's a lot
to say about this. We can draw from, you
know, ancient [clears throat]
philosophy, Aristotle, Plato, and from
Christian philosophy as well. But
probably there's one word that can
summarize this, I think, quite well.
It's the fact that our intelligence is
embodied. So, we're not just spirits
like flying around, but we're we're body
and soul, right? Unity of body and soul.
That's that's what a human being is. And
my intelligence is embodied. So the way
I know is through the senses.
So I see something, I perceive
something, right? I hear something and
then I abstract from what I earn from my
senses a concept, right? That helps me
know the reality. That's that's the way
human thinking, human intelligence
works. And AI is not embodied. So it's
never experienced. It's never touch
anything, right? is never scrape it
sneezed and all that. So it's embodied
and therefore human intelligence is also
relational
and the way I know something is through
relationships with
>> things with persons with people right
>> so so AI is good at so many things
but I think it's not quite good at
unpredictable circumstances right that
requires creativity immediate responses
that's you see all those self-driving
cars right and And you can read I mean
on the internet what happened to those
self-driving cars right when they park
and so
why a human driver is still better than
self-driving cars right if it were not
then we would have had like self-driving
cars anywhere right everywhere
>> but is is the capability to respond to
um myriad of situations unpredictable
situations that human being why because
we have experienced it because our
knowledge is embodied
And father, what do you think we lose by
using chat GPT every day? Do you think
there's something that the average, you
know, student is losing a a critical,
you know, learning experience? I I
wonder about this often as I as I see
also in my personal life, you know,
using using these AI tools more and more
often for for mundane tasks. But I I
wonder you know when I was in undergrad
I didn't have you know an AI and so I
every every paper I I wrote and that was
I know that there was value in that and
I and I wonder with these young students
as more and more technological tools
which which are tools which means
there's lots of good um but as that as
that those opportunities and those
options are made available it becomes
harder and harder to say well I'm not
going to take that you know that that
opportunity to to do something quicker
or do something more efficiently
>> right I think There's something one
loses when one is heavily relying on AI
tools. First one is this the artistal
aspect of thinking.
>> Mhm.
>> Right. When when I we use AI to resemble
let's say draft an email, right? Or
write something up. Yeah. You you get
from point A to point B, right? Getting
the email done and sent, but then you
haven't gone through it. It's it's not
something uh it's not embodied, right?
Yeah,
>> it's like, okay, I want to
>> we talked about like walking or jogging
earlier. Okay, I want to get my steps
in, but I'm just going to drive from,
you know, here and and then I don't
know, turn on the app or something and
and let it register it as my steps,
right? I get my steps in, but I haven't
walked those steps, right? Those miles.
>> So, I think it's similar, right? Or
riding a bike or any we can find all
sorts of analogies. So the first is okay
it's not embodied you haven't done it
that's why at least I try every day to
dedicate
certain time to unaded writing unaded
thinking so I I don't use Gemini or GPD
or anything I write I write the the old
school way just type I mean type or you
know better even if we can write
handwrite but I I just type with
probably with errors with you know with
I type but this helps me think right and
there's the second thing we lose as well
if we are heavily dependent on AI tools
I think it's
our humanity or the human character of
our products
>> it's like when reading emails I can
sense I I don't want to say I I can know
like 100% this is AI generated or not
but when an email contains a small error
now I rejoice in it it's like when I
receive an email with a small error
right Oh, this person has put the time
into writing the email
>> without the aid of AI, right? I'm I'm
I'm valued. I'm [clears throat]
>> I I work his time, right? Is before I
was like, this typo, right? And now I I
marvel at it. I mean, wow. I marvel at
it. And people write with errors.
>> Absolutely. And they think with errors
and they they've talked with errors.
>> Grammatical errors here and there,
right? It's fine. And is I mean it's not
fine but you know it's it's it
demonstrates humanity right and when the
emails are perfect but it's it's written
with without AI I can sense it as well
because the language it uses right the
variety of verbs used in the email or or
writings we can apply this to articles
right so our humanity
>> yeah and then father I wanted to ask um
when you're when you're talking to your
students and when you're teaching a
class and you mentioned you know that
it's quite international often. Um what
do you notice about different students
from different parts of the world? Are
is the format of education different? Is
the work ethic different? Is um the
attention to certain tasks different?
like what what makes you know a student
from a Roman student, an Italian student
here who's you know studying to be a
priest seminarian uh in your class
different from let's say someone from
the United States from from North Africa
from from Asia you know what what do you
see in the in the educational history
you know and the traditions of education
as being different or as markers
>> all generalize a lot I think but yeah
but that's a great question because
every geographical area has its own
idiosyncrasy right in in learning and
approaching education. I think in at
least in Europe this is a broad strokes
right in Europe the
students are used to this lecture style
where it's very [clears throat]
magisterial I mean right it's like okay
teach frontal classes we call it in
Italian right it's like face to face and
the teacher talking exposing right the
whole thing what I like about the
education in the states
is that the students students have to be
active as well. They have to put in
something, right? So,
they're more used to discussion formats,
right? Group works and then probably
presentation. Oh, this is a little bit
less common in Europe. I
>> I noticed that because I remember I took
a class here and um it was a philosophy
class because I I adore philosophy and
it was completely lecture-based and I
found it very tedious. Even though the
the the professor was wonderful, I was
antsy. And I I remember uh in undergrad
and graduate school and of course in
high school in the US, very projects
based, you know, okay, the professor
gives or the teacher gives a gives an
opening statement and then okay, break
off into small groups, come back with
something and I and I love that creative
kind of entrepreneurial aspect.
>> Oh yeah, it's more more dynamic, right?
Well, this this has a long history in
Europe because the word lecture itself
comes from leger, right? In in Latin,
lexio, right, is reading. I mean, before
what what did professors do? They read.
I mean, I mean I mean we try not to do
it nowadays, right? And we know it's not
useful. So,
>> brilliant lecture, but but I just was
antsy to get get up and do something.
>> Exactly. Exactly. So I I think with with
I mean with in this technological age I
think Alexio like the the traditional
form of lecture is not enough right and
in Asia I think it's more project based
as well in in so many places so it's um
with the involvement of students group
works and the of course the the the
emphasis on certain aspects is different
for every student right
>> yeah and then father as you as you um I
know you're you you're very involved in
in in the tech space and very kind of
forward thinking with AI. Um when you
look at your students, how are you
equipping them for this kind of this new
age that we're we're entering where um
where work and education will be viewed
in some lenses, you know, different I
mean the same as as as I loved as you
mentioned education being a pursuit of
the truth and that having a vocational
aspect and and I really do hope that
that you know the technology is going to
put an emphasis on the education being
about the the profounder truths rather
than just getting a job. But h how are
you preparing your your students to to
navigate and to be guided into this kind
of this new tech age that we're
entering?
>> The one thing I do is I want you to be
active learners, right? Because AI
sometimes
can encourage a person to be passive,
right? Okay, you put a prompt in, at
least that's something active, right?
You put a prompt in and then okay, you
receive everything and then okay, you
just swallow everything that AI spits
out. But I try to uh remind them of the
importance of being active. So before
for example before the class day I
assign readings. I assign readings and I
prepared for them not only the the text
should be read but also study questions.
They have to try to answer those
questions based on the readings. So
that's something active. Now they come
to the class already with this framework
in their mind of of things that might be
covered. And so it's you have the ground
kind of tilt a little bit, right? But
I'm active learners and
at least me with my the [clears throat]
ordinary professor and my boss at the
university who teaches Trinity as well.
We we discourage really you know just
putting the PDF of the text into AI and
then have [clears throat] it generate a
summary. You haven't you you're not
through it, right? is is so you just
read it slowly, right? So we encourage
we do encourage this artisal thinking,
right? Reading, digesting a text, being
in contact in touch with sources, right?
Primary sources. I think that's
important. And yeah, that's that's one
of the ways I try to encourage my
students to should to be just artisal
like, you know, just use your hands and
>> Right. And and do you think the
pontipical universities by and large are
are adapting to AI or utilizing it for
for its its positive potential? Like how
do you see you know center for example
um I know in the US for example there's
usually an AI task force that's been
something that's happened in the last
few years around the majority of the
universities. Now I don't I don't know
clearly you know what what each one is
doing but they they typically have
professors or researchers or graduate
students kind of saying okay cool this
is what the technology does. How are we
how are we utilizing it for the best
better the betterment of the university
and the students to come? Uh do you see
the Pentipal universities or Santa
Crochce kind of developing their
curriculum or looking at new research
projects around around this stuff?
>> They do. At least I can speak for Santa
Crochce, right? I think um
many [clears throat] professors see this
as an important thing to do, right? Just
to tackle this because Santa Crochce was
founded by the inspiration of St. Jose
Maria Scarva right so um this
sanctification of our life in the world
right and and we have to face the world
and we are in the middle of the world
and we cannot just this disregard
contemporary culture and one of them is
AI of course right we have to see how we
can um leverage AI and um help people
use it well as well so at least some
professors are conceiving a work group
right kind of you as you said like task
force probably at the practical level
right more more on how we can leverage
AI in the university and at the faculty
meeting a while ago where I presented on
AI I also discovered that actually
a good number of professors are really
forward thinking and and they're
probably using AI in a way more
sophisticated than I do right they they
can code in Python and you know use the
API and everything and you know we have
really sophisticated professors
And I was happy to see that, right?
Because they're trying to leverage AI
for research, right? Or to to advance
research, right? Finding something,
finding a source and not to offload
thinking, but then to go themselves to
those sources and then start the
thinking process already with, you know,
with with with knowing where to go,
right?
>> Yeah. And then father, if you were to
kind of look into the future, do you
anticipate more classrooms having, you
know, a holographic father Kenny, you
know, providing, you know, a lecture or
do do you think that, you know, classes
are going to maybe become more lite in
the sense of kind of like, okay, in the
classroom actually we're not going to
have the technology. We're going to just
have this hour together and and talk
about these things and work through them
and then at home you can, you know, do
your coding or look through the the
material and have your smartphones. What
do you what do you think the h what
direction do you think the the the
classroom settings are going to become
kind of
>> I think the second case is more
appealing to me. [clears throat]
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> I I think same thing we experience
through co
>> Mhm. would be recurring this time with
AI because when at co as I mentioned
earlier oh there was this frenzy about
online thing and everything oh so useful
we could have done this like a long time
ago why didn't we but now we we're
saying oh we don't want all that right
we want we want this direct
>> absolutely
>> inerson contact right now I think with
AI is the same now is there's this all
this frenzy and there's people call it
bubble and again and the economic term
uh excitement right but then I think in
the end if uh people are reflecting or
reflective enough on AI they'll realize
that oh I'm missing out actually I value
other things more than just getting this
you know answers from AI than just I
value
thinking by myself for example right
>> I value discussing with others right I
value
you um confronting my ideas to other
people and that requires you know the
immediiacy of a classroom experience. So
I think I I think in the future I don't
know I'm I'm not a prophet or anything
but I think in the future we could see
classroom sessions probably shorter
right not lecture oriented we already
have so many professors nowadays not
giving lectures right in classes but
professors are like moderators right
they're [clears throat] they're they're
moderating their students it's more
socratic it's more like Socrates trying
to help the students obtain the answers
for themselves right? Like you know the
midwife the midwife analogy, right? So I
I see education going that direction and
hopefully that could be helpful in this
age. And father in terms of um uh like
for looking at the priesthood for
example and looking looking at um you
know educating education becoming
something more focused on that
vocational pursuit of the truth like the
the deeper truths and and if you know we
manage to be guided in this transition
where you know people have more time and
the technology is really helping people
spend more time on the things that are
important. One of the one of the
questions and one of the conversations I
I fell in with with a with a wonderful
priest was talking about kind of, you
know, hopefully a a vocational boom in
the sense that that young men who
finally have the time to focus on the on
the deeper things will feel this call to
the the you know, the deepest adventure
and following in the footstep of of
Christ. Do you do you see do you see
that happening? I mean a lot of people
are talking about you know for example
in the United States right now where a
lot of young men are um because also of
the technology providing an outlet where
people all of a sudden you know this is
this kind of funny but during one of the
conversations we had with the BAFE
webinar um you know people having these
existential questions and looking online
you know at 2 in the morning and
actually they're listening to you know
to lectures by Jordan Peterson or
they're or they're you know they're
listening to to lectures by by Bishop
Baron and feeling you know the the
technology in a weird way whispering in
that heroic vocation that that was there
But maybe now with a little bit more
calm people can really respond to that
call.
>> I do think so. And only not only to
priesthood, I think also to married
life, right?
>> Because if there's something unaliable,
it's probably the priesthood, right? One
of the things uniable also being a
father is not aable, right? Being a
mother, right? Being a parent, that's
not aable. Um yeah I I the a big chunk
of the big part of my classroom and my
students are those preparing for a
priesthood right there's one thing I
think I said to seminarian or a friend
there's a skill a priest or a seminarian
needed to learn and also as a priest is
listening right and and that's why we
need to really fight against this
attention deficit right you I mean can
you still maintain a sustained
listening, having all those distractions
around you, right? How can you
prioritize things you ingest every day
as a human person, right? I think this
awareness of AI being a tool and
shouldn't be a distraction is very
important along this line. Yeah, I think
it it'll help boost vocations if we
educate people enough about what AI can
and cannot do, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah. And I think the the most
important skill is what you just
mentioned, which is kind of being able
to say no to the distractions cuz I feel
like that's a skill set that at least in
the in the west, but in the modern
world, it seems like any piece of
technology is good, cool. We're going to
use it without really thinking about
also what it is taking away. I mean, the
tools that we have around the
smartphone, around social media, around
kind of that noise. We didn't as a
community, as a society have a
conversation about what the cost of that
would be. I mean, it's a fantastic tool
because information is is being shared.
There's a horizontal kind of level of
information where it's not just vertical
where there's just a few outlets. It's
great that people have the ability to to
to share to talk and all that stuff. But
the cost is that it seems like people a
can't really have a real conversation
anymore, don't know how to listen, and
can't really focus. And I don't really
know how you build those skills in when
there isn't much in the society that is
encouraging that. I mean, there's the
interior and there's the church, but
>> Right. Right. And sometimes parents are
the worst, right? Because it's something
you learn at home, but then you see your
parents all engrossed in a phone, right,
during meals and that's not very
helpful, is it? So yeah, is is yeah
learning to focus and I think people are
not naive because there's this rise of
for example dumb phones. Have you right?
I mean people are naive because they see
that oh smartphones are not helping
anymore so I'm going to switch to dumb
phones. Flip phone. A traditional
>> flip phone, right? Noia, right?
>> No Wi-Fi.
>> No Wi-Fi, right?
>> Call and text. That's it.
>> Exactly. [clears throat] Exactly. I know
actually a a fraternity of priest. So,
it's a community of priests, right, here
in based in I think based in Italy,
right? And they're missionaries. So,
they have this kind of policy they
embrace uh joyfully, right? They So, the
f during the first years of formation,
they don't have phones. And when they
reach I I don't know I'm not sure fifth
year sixth year formation they can have
a dumb phone right dumb phone that can
you can use WhatsApp right and then the
they continue using dumb phones when
they're priests right unless for work
purpose you need a smartphone right
because because for work you need it but
you know people are not naive I think we
if we spread this word and people will
realize what's good and not right
eventually
>> and father when if you if when you look
at you know parents with their younger
children and you know they're having the
conversations around at what age do I
give a smartphone to my child? What what
what do you recommend? I mean I would I
would think you know until you're 18 you
should not have a smartphone but but um
but I mean there's you know questions
around okay well when they go into
seventh grade is it when they go to
sixth grade is it when they're you know
because I I think there is a difference
between a smartphone that has the the
screen and the YouTube and all that
stuff which is very addictive. I see it
with my my little children. uh you know
any any screen they become hypnotic they
become you know they kind of lose almost
in a weird way self-control. Um what
what do you see? What what do you
recommend?
>> I know at least a family they they live
in Wisconsin and a good Catholic family
and they don't give phones to their kids
until they are in college as you said.
So they're like 18 or something. Uh so
their their rule is when you can drive
you can have your phone
>> right because when you don't drive then
you probably don't need a phone you're
at home with right if you you go
somewhere you won't go that far away or
probably you'll go with somebody else
right you don't drive
>> right so a phone is not needed and
you're right I I have nephews and I have
a niece as well and you know I think
kids are really good at telling that
you're not focused right% when when your
eyes are not looking at them. You're
you're looking at your phone, you're
doing something else, right? They're
good at, you know, detecting, you know,
attention deficit, right? They're very
good at it. And they actually long for
that attention, right?
>> Oh, yeah. The exclusive attention. They
want they don't want the the distracted
here's your dad is texting while he's
listening to me, but he's not, you know.
>> Nope. Nope. And I I think I watched a
video or I read something explaining
that it's not good for the child, right?
So they need to uh feel and know that
you're giving all your attention to
them, right? So it's it's very u
important for us to learn. I'm not a
parent, but you know, for parents to
really learn that. I know it's easier to
give them an iPad, right? And and and
play a video. It's easier. It's is a
shortcut for so many people, but I think
it's it would be heroic. That's the
normal thing, right? That's that's
natural, but it'd be supernatural. It
would be heroic and I think God would
really reward it if No, I'm I I don't
want to just take the shortcut of giving
screens to my kids. I I want to
accompany them myself. It's tedious.
It's tiring, right?
>> Absolutely.
>> But it's um very rewarding, I think. And
so, Father Kenny, as we kind of wrap up
this conversation and we look towards
the future, um, as you know, a Catholic
priest teaching here in Rome and, you
know, we have um, you know, the holy
father who, um, is is very focused also
on artificial intelligence and the
questions that kind of guide this
podcast. What role would you like to see
the the institutional church take in
guiding us through this convers through
this transition this technological
transition that we have here with AI and
people looking at the future and not you
know of course we of course as faithful
you know we we're guided by hope and
we're guided by the certainty of the the
promises of Christ but you know I I know
that Christians have experienced
uncertainty in the future you know in
all stages in all historical periods but
it seems that at this moment a lot of
that uncertainty is around technology um
what role would you want the church to
have um and you know and and and the
formal church you know in guiding us
through this this moment in time. First
of all, we know that Christ is the same,
right? Christ will not change yesterday,
today, and tomorrow. He'll be the same.
And nor would teachings of the church,
right? But the situations we live in do
change. And I think the [clears throat]
church has a big role, a consequential
role in accompanying the Catholics, but
not only human beings, right? In
general, accompanying people in this
vicissitudes, right?
technological changes and transitions.
Matthew Matthew Sanders, CEO of
Longbeard, uh talk about this a lot, you
know, the use of time for example,
right? I I love to explain because once
AI is getting better, right? Getting
better. Uh we will have more time at our
disposal, right? But the question is
what are you going to use it for, right?
How will you use your time? Probably
will work less, right? with all these
technologies aiding us. Now the question
of how we will use time I think that's
the the task of the church to help
people answer that right are we going to
indulge in I don't know sins or you know
addictions or we have other ways of
using our time better right now that's
already we are entering we we are
passing from only technological realm to
moral realm what am I going to use my
time for I'm going to help others Right?
I'm going to dedicate my time to really
study more so I can explain faith better
to others or spending more time with my
family. Now, that's the moral realm
where the church has a lot to say. The
church will not pronounce anything about
the technicalities of how AI should
work. Right now, the church's focus is
the human person.
>> Yeah. No, I love that. I love that,
father. And as um as education has also
you know changed over time I think of
you know the educational formats um you
know in the 1800s and the 1700s it was
very much about you know aristocracy you
know being formation of the mind and all
that and then you you look you know down
the centuries to much more of a
formational kind of apprenticeship role
and then now you know with the liberal
arts with the with um you know the
private universities that are you know
really cultivating kind of the social
studies and all that things have
changed. How do you see education
changing and adapting with with this
technology? Um do you think that you
know with that more time we're going to
we're going to focus more on the
formation the moral virtues the the
philosophical and the theological you
know um deepening our understanding of
that or and do you do you think also
that there will be a path where people
are more in apprenticeships and more in
you know finding technical skills for
the technical problems they're they're
facing. I think both. You mentioned a
very good point there. Apprenticeship,
right? I see so many news headlines that
go something like go blue collar, right?
With with all these AI, right? Now, who
who are the first to lose their
positions or jobs? I think entry level,
you know, white collar jobs, right? At
the moment, is that right? Am I right?
Right. So, people say go blue color, be
a plumber or something. Right. So,
something I I said artal, right? That's
something you apprenticeship.
>> I love that framing. Yeah.
>> Right. Just something you can do with
your hands, right? Meaning handwriting,
right? You know, uh communication skill.
Oh, I mean that's another big big topic
we didn't touch, right? How you
communicate will distinguish you from
others, right? So, I think education
should go that direction. At the same
time, I think there's another shift,
right? Because education will also deal
with technology, right? And we have to
educate our students how to use
technology well. And in this realm I
think the shift will be from forming
just generators of content because
before our focus was hey you need to
generate contents right you you're a
journalist and you learn how to write
news write articles and all that right
>> but now I think with so many noise
around us right so many fake news as
well or deep fakes what we have to form
people to be good at is how to evaluate
content right not only to generate
content Because I think AI is pretty
good at generating so many things right
now. How you evaluate even the contents
generated by AI for example that's going
to be fundamental.
>> Mhm. And then father last question here
um are you optimistic about the future?
What gives you hope? future in general.
>> Future in general and visav um you know
kind of the the arc of the conversation
with technology AI education and you
know for the I'm thinking specifically
of the young high schoolers who are
getting ready you know to do their
applications this fall for for
university and who are wondering um you
know what what future they're going to
be you know applying for in that sense.
Um there's just a a quick note um in a
in a previous conversation uh we had a a
young man from uh Boston who saw an
advertisement um uh and the
advertisement was with AI robots and
they were saying don't hire humans. I we
might have spoken about this but the the
advertisement was specifically don't
hire humans and these were very you know
human humanes AIs and they you know they
they were of course you know making an
advertisement for for that AI company to
do your coding and to do all that stuff
but um but this uh this young man uh
went to his professor who was a priest
and he said um you know what's the point
father I'm a I'm a good student I'm in a
good college but there's no way you know
you look at the advancements in AI
generated code in the last couple years
and it's phenomenal now I mean it's not
perfect of course but it's you most
entry-level coders, you know, are are in
competition now and trying to justify
their their their role. And you look at
that trajectory in the other fields, you
know what, you know, obviously technical
fields are easier for an AI and for you
know, kind of a mechanistic um mind to
to replicate. But um but this young man
was very very depressed and um you look
at the AI chat bots and you know the the
amount of online relationships that
people are having where they're not with
people, they're with AI. you know, you
start to look at that and that is you
mean I'm I'm optimistic in the sense
that I I think that of course um the
good will outweigh the bad and I I feel
that genuinely and I'm I'm one I'm very
excited about kind of how technology can
help the human condition but um but this
young man was uh was very very nervous
and I think justifiably so and I I think
you know I look at my son who's who's
almost four and I look at the next you
know let's say 14 years when by the time
he's 18 and he's applying for college
I'm like what what is the world going to
look like And you know, of course, I'm
I'm optimistic and I think that the work
that we're doing is wonderful, but but
um but there there are a lot of people
who who are looking at the future with
that trepidation, with that sense of
anxiety, and because of course
technology is moving very very quickly,
it is hard to find the markers. And and
I I wonder with you, Father, as someone
who, you know, works with with with
university students and who um of course
is is is looking at this through the
Catholic lens, where you know, what
gives you hope? And also, are you are
you genuinely optimistic about um about
the direction we're going with all this?
>> I think my answer is yes and no.
No, because I I don't believe in
progress for the sake of progress,
right? You know, like this there's this
current of thought where they think that
things will always go for the better.
Not always. I think
>> yeah,
>> probably my [clears throat] my father is
better than me, right? So it's not like
you know I don't believe in progress for
the sake of progress
>> and looking at the situation right now
>> there are a lot to be worried about%
[laughter]
>> right so as you said I think I don't
have to underline this enough right
>> the the state of our
>> church of the faith and society right of
you know different currents of thoughts
and you know not to mention wars and
everything a lot to worry about so on
the one hand I'm not optimistic
On the other hand, I am optimistic in
the sense that I'm hopeful
because this is I'm a Christian, you
know, and Christian hope, you know, I'm
the the the good we are aiming at is God
himself right in heaven and he will help
us. um not only because of that but I
mostly because of God's help of course
but then there's another factor I also
considering is that there are
good people to to just speak broadly
good people faithful Catholics and good
probably doesn't have to be Catholic
right you know there are good people in
different parts of the world and somehow
we're going towards um a better
direction right We're thinking about how
things could be better, right? We're
thinking about how we can face this
challenge.
But the thing is we're not connected,
right? I think um it's very important to
build a network nowadays because okay,
you can be good but if you are alone
then you you won't be able to tackle all
these challenges right
civilization threatening challenges
right that AI poses or or other things
pose. So I think we got to build this
network right of good people going
together right and [clears throat] for
Christians this is also
um a means for bringing the faith right
of giving witness to our faith right hey
let's work together you're not Catholic
you're not Christian but we want to
strive towards the same good right and
and work together and I think this is
very beautiful in this time so yes I'm
optimistic hopeful uh even though I'm
not very optimistic sick about so many
things, but we have a lot to um work on
and and I think God will always help us.
[clears throat] That's our hope.
>> Beautiful. Well, Father Kenyang, thank
you so much for this conversation.
>> Thank you, Ben. Thank you. I've enjoyed
it.